Finding Aid for the glatzer buber
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Buber Collection
multiple
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0000b
.01 linear_feet
- I. Manuscripts
  - A. Tales of the Hasidim (Die Erzählungen der Chassidim)
    - “Reihenfolge des I Bandes” (Outline for vol I) (manuscript, p. 1) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - “Anordnung in Tales II” (25.II.47) (manuscript, pp. 2) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - “Die Nachkommen des grossen Maggids” (selected masters) (manuscript, pp. 26) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - “Mosche Leib von Sasow” (manuscript, pp. 13) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - “Abraham Jehoschua Heschel von Apta” (manuscript, pp. 14) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - “Menachem Mendel von Rymanow” (manuscript, pp. 13) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - “Uri von Strelisk” (manuscript, pp. 6) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - “Jehuda Zwi von Stretyn und sein Sohn Abraham von Stretyn” (manuscript, pp. 3) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - “Menachim Mendel von Kozk” (manuscript, pp. 26) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - “Mordecai von Lechowitz und seine Nachkommen” (manuscript, pp. 9) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - “Mosche von Kobryn” (manuscript, pp. 15) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - “Naftalis von Ropuchitz” (manuscript, script, pp. 5) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - “Jaakob Jizchak von Psysha (des “Jehudi”) und seine Nachkommen” (manuscript, pp. 14) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - “Simcha Bunam von Psysha” (File #1 of 2) (manuscript, pp. 1-20) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - “Simcha Bunam von Psysha” (File #2 of 2) (manuscript, pp. 21-35) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - B. Martin Buber’s Corrections to English Translation
    - “Preface” (manuscript, pp. 2) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - “End of the Preface” (manuscript, pp. 2) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - “Introduction to Tales II (manuscript, pp. 10) (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - (manuscript, p. 1) (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Selected masters (manuscript, pp. 12) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Selected masters (manuscript, pp. 7) (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Selected masters (manuscript, pp.2) (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Selected masters (manuscript, pp. 3) (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - (manuscript, pp. 3 and 1 note) (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Selected masters (manuscript, pp. 8 and 1 note) (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Selected masters (manuscript, pp. 5) (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Selected masters (manuscript, pp. 6 and 1 note) (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Selected masters (manuscript, pp. 5 and 1 note) (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Selected masters (manuscript, pp. 4) (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - (manuscript, pp. 4) (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - (manuscript, pp. 14) (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - (manuscript, pp. 4) (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Final corrections (manuscript, pp. 2) (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Final corrections (manuscript, p. 1) (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Corrections to end notes (manuscript, p. 1) (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - C. Glossar (German)
    - Glossar and NNG additions to Glossar (manuscript, pp. 6) (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - D. Glossary and Definition of Terms (English)
    - Glossary (manuscript, pp. 19) (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Glossary (typescript, pp. 16) (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Additions to the glossary [(1) manuscript and (2) typescript, pp. 3] (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - E. Notes re. Index
    - Notes (manuscript, pp. 2) (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - F. Notes re. Martin Buber Lectures and Seminars
    - “Der heutige Mensch und die Bibel” (11.12.1928) (manuscript, pp. 17) (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - “Die Prophetie” (winter semester 1929/30) (manuscript, pp. 17) (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - “Der Glaube und die allgemeine. Religionswissenschaft” (1.2.28) (manuscript, pp. 2) (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - “Biblische Religion und Religionswissenschaft” (1927-28)(manuscript, pp. 23) (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - “Religiongeschichtliche Übungen” (summer semester 1931) (manuscript, pp. 15 and 1 note page) (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - “Glaube und Bräuche” (winter semester 1930-31) (original manuscript, pp. 26 and copy, typescript, pp. 17), 1 summary (11 February 1931) (typescript, pp. 2), “manuscript (2.18.31) manuscript (2.25.31) (manuscript, pp. 9) (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - “Grundbegriffe der Religionswissenschaft” (winter semester 1931/32) (manuscript, pp. 19) (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - “Der Erlöser” (summer semester 1932) (manuscript, pp. 7) (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - “Die Idee der Wiedergeburt” (summer semester 1931) (manuscript, pp. 20 and 1 note) (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - “Messianismus” (winter semester 1924-25) (manuscript, pp. 14) (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - “Ponte Tresa” (manuscript, pp. 27) (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - “Vom Übersetzen der Schrift” (winter semester 1928-29) (manuscript, pp. 28) (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - “Schöpfungsmythen” (winter semester 1925-26) (manuscript, pp. 39) (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - “Die Formen der Religionen” (pages missing? part of “Gebet”? - Folder #56) (manuscript, pp. 10, 1-6 and 19-22) (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - “Religion und Philosophie” (24.5.29) (manuscript, pp. 9) (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - “Gebet” (pages missing? part of “Die Formen der Religionen”? - Folder #54) (manuscript, pp. 8) (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - “Probleme des Gottesnamens” (winter semester 1926/27) (manuscript, pp. 22) (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - “Wie ist Religionswissenschaft möglich?” (summer semester 1926) (manuscript, pp. 19) (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - “Religion als Gegenwart” (8 lectures) May, 1922 (manuscript, pp. 7+) (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - “Baal-Schem” (summer semester 1923) (manuscript, pp. 5) (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - “Das Wesen der Religion” (manuscript, pp. 14) (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - “Etwas über Gotteserzeuge”(Gen 12-50) (Lehrhaus) (manuscript, pp. 6) (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - “Notizen zur Aussprache Buber-Schaff” (Lehrhaus 1926) (manuscript, pp. 11) (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Buber's lectures, Title (?) (Winter semester? 1932/33) (manuscript, pp. 2) (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Buber's lectures? (manuscript, pp. 2, 4 used in article) (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - G. Translations
    - Martin Buber? (manuscript, p. 1) (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Martin Buber? (manuscript, pp. 3) (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Martin Buber? (manuscript, pp. 8) (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Martin Buber? (manuscript, pp. 21) (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Martin Buber? (manuscript, pp. 11, 15) (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Martin Buber? (manuscript, pp. 14, 16, 11, 9) (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Martin Buber? (11-13.VI.26) (manuscript, pp. 89) (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - H. Vorwort to “Zion und die nationalen Ideen” (manuscript, pp. 2 sheets, 3 used) (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - I. Poems
    - “Gottes Wirken” (typescript, p. 1), “Mitar- beit des Menschen” (typescript, p. 1) and “Heute!” (typescript, p. 1) (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - J. Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous items (manuscript and typescript) (pp. 5) (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Miscellaneous items (manuscript and typescript) (pp. 9) (Box 2, Folder 76)
- II. Correspondence
  - A. Letters from MB to NNG
    - A1-A15 (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - A16-A25, A27, A29, A30 (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - A31-A35, A42-A45 (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - A46-A54 (manuscript and typescript) (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - #1-#10 (1945-46) (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - #11-#20 (1946) (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - #21-#30 (1946) (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - #31-#40 (1946-47) (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - #41-#50 (1947) (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - #51-#60 (1947) (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - #61-#70 (1947-48) (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - #71-#80 (1948) (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - #81-#90 (1948) (manuscript and typescript) (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - #91-#100 (1948) (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - #101-#110 (1949) (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - #111-#120 (1949-50) (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - #121-#130 (1950-51) (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - #131-#140 (1951-54) (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - #141-#149 (1956-60) (manuscript and typescript) (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - 1948 letter and 1 extra sheet of information? (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - 1961 letter: From MB to NNG (typescript) (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Letters (1946, 1948) (typescript, includes copies) (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - B. Notes from MB to NNG (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - C. Various letters re. Buber to NNG from various individuals (typescript) (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - D. Various letters re. Buber by NNG (manuscript and typescript) (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - E. Various notes re. Buber by NNG (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - F. Dated information letters re. Buber by NNG (manuscript, copies) (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - G. Letters re. MB from various individuals
    - Aubrey Hodes (typescript, photostat) (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Schwarzschild (manuscript, typescript, copy) (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Carol Schoen (typescript) (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - Leo Baeck
      - manuscript (10) (Box 2, Folder 107)
      - File #1 - (manuscript) (9) (Box 2, Folder 108)
      - File #2 - (manuscript and typescript) (9) (Box 2, Folder 109)
      - air mail (manuscript and typescript) (8) (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - Leo Baeck and Ruth Berlak (manuscript and off-print) (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Ruth Pinsky (1.11.1949) (typescript, copies) (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - H. Letters to MB from NNG (9.27.1948 and 12.7.1948) (typescript, copies) (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - I. Correspondence/Schocken Books
    - Buber letters (1946) (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 114)
    - Buber letters (1947) (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 115)
    - Buber letters (1950) (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 116)
    - MB and Raphael (letters and notes)
      - File #1 (manuscript, typescript, photostats) (Box 2, Folder 117)
      - File #2 (typescript, copies) (Box 2, Folder 118)
      - File #3 (typescript, copies) (Box 2, Folder 119)
      - File #4 (typescript, copies) (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - Letters re. Buber from Eva Jospe and NNG (manuscript, typescript, copies; includes 1 letter to Hanna Gunther from NNG) (Box 2, Folder 121)
    - Letters re. Buber (typescript, copies) (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - Schocken letters (1946) (typescript, copies) (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - NNG/Schocken letters (1966) (manuscript and typescript) (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - J. Telegrams? (manuscript, typescript, copy) (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - K. Postcards from MB to NNG (manuscript) (Box 2, Folder 126)
  - L. Letter - Dremel Manufacturing Co. (10.21.1949) (manuscript and typescript) (Box 2, Folder 127)
- III. The Scriptures, German (Die Schrift, verdeutcht von Martin Buber, gemeinsam mit Franz Rosenzweig)
  - A. Isaiah (Jeschajahu)
    - (manuscript, pp. 1-7) (Box 2, Folder 128)
    - (manuscript, pp. 8-15) (Box 2, Folder 129)
    - (manuscript, pp. 16-24) (Box 2, Folder 130)
    - (manuscript, pp. 25-35) (Box 2, Folder 131)
    - (manuscript, pp. 36-46) (Box 2, Folder 132)
    - (manuscript, pp. 47-56) (Box 2, Folder 133)
    - (manuscript, pp. 57-64) (Box 2, Folder 134)
    - (manuscript, pp. 65-70) (Box 2, Folder 135)
    - (manuscript, pp. 71-81) (Box 2, Folder 136)
    - (manuscript, pp. 82-88) (Box 2, Folder 137)
    - (manuscript, pp. 89-95) (Box 2, Folder 138)
    - (manuscript, pp. 96-103) (Box 2, Folder 139)
  - B. Exodus (Namen)
    - (manuscript, pp. 1-13) (Box 2, Folder 140)
    - (manuscript, pp. 14-21) (Box 2, Folder 141)
    - (manuscript, pp. 22-33) (Box 2, Folder 142)
    - (manuscript, pp. 34-48) (Box 2, Folder 143)
    - (manuscript, pp. 49-60) (Box 2, Folder 144)
    - (manuscript, pp. 61-71) (Box 2, Folder 145)
    - (manuscript, pp. 72-81) (Box 2, Folder 146)
  - C. Kings (Könige)
    - (manuscript, pp. 1-7a) (Box 3, Folder 147)
    - (manuscript, pp. 8-15) (Box 3, Folder 148)
    - (manuscript, pp. 16-23) (Box 3, Folder 149)
    - (manuscript, pp. 24-30) (Box 3, Folder 150)
    - (manuscript, pp. 31-37) (Box 3, Folder 151)
    - (manuscript, pp. 38-45) (Box 3, Folder 152)
    - (manuscript, pp. 46-57) (Box 3, Folder 153)
    - (manuscript, pp. 58-66) (Box 3, Folder 154)
    - (manuscript, pp. 67-73) (Box 3, Folder 155)
    - (manuscript, pp. 74-84) (Box 3, Folder 156)
    - (manuscript, pp. 85-92) (Box 3, Folder 157)
    - (manuscript, pp. 93-101a) (Box 3, Folder 158)
    - (manuscript, pp. 102-110) (Box 3, Folder 159)
    - (manuscript, pp. 111-119) (Box 3, Folder 160)
    - (manuscript, pp. 120-125) (Box 3, Folder 161)
    - (manuscript, pp. 126-132) (Box 3, Folder 162)
  - D. Leviticus (In der Wüste)
    - (manuscript, pp. 1-6a) (Box 3, Folder 163)
    - (manuscript, pp. 7-12) (Box 3, Folder 164)
    - (manuscript, pp. 13-17) (Box 3, Folder 165)
    - (manuscript, pp. 18-21) (Box 3, Folder 166)
  - E. Deuteronomy (Reden)
    - (manuscript, pp. 1-7) (Box 3, Folder 167)
    - (manuscript, pp. 8-13) (Box 3, Folder 168)
    - (manuscript, pp. 14-20) (Box 3, Folder 169)
    - (manuscript, pp. 21-27) (Box 3, Folder 170)
    - (manuscript, pp. 28-36) (Box 3, Folder 171)
    - (manuscript, pp. 37-46a and addenda) (Box 3, Folder 172)
  - F. Joshua (Jehoschua)
    - (manuscript, pp. 1-7a) (Box 3, Folder 173)
  - G. Judges (Richter)
    - (manuscript, pp. 1-7) (Box 3, Folder 174)
    - (manuscript, pp. 8-14a) (Box 3, Folder 175)
    - (manuscript, pp. 15-23a) (Box 3, Folder 176)
    - (manuscript, pp. 24-29) (Box 3, Folder 177)
    - (manuscript, pp. 30-39) (Box 3, Folder 178)
    - (manuscript, pp. 40-44) (Box 3, Folder 179)
  - H. Samuel (Schmuel)
    - (manuscript, pp. 1-7a) (Box 3, Folder 180)
    - (manuscript, pp. 8-16) (Box 3, Folder 181)
    - (manuscript, pp. 17-23a) (Box 3, Folder 182)
    - (manuscript, pp. 24-31) (Box 3, Folder 183)
    - (manuscript, pp. 32-39) (Box 3, Folder 184)
    - (manuscript, pp. 40-45) (Box 3, Folder 185)
    - (manuscript, pp. 46-52) (Box 3, Folder 186)
    - (manuscript, pp. 53-60) (Box 3, Folder 187)
    - (manuscript, pp. 61-70) (Box 3, Folder 188)
    - (manuscript, pp. 71-78) (Box 3, Folder 189)
    - (manuscript, pp. 79-84) (Box 3, Folder 190)
    - (manuscript, pp. 85-92) (Box 3, Folder 191)
    - (manuscript, pp. 93-103) (Box 3, Folder 192)
  - I. Numbers (Er rief)
    - (manuscript, pp. 1-7) (Box 3, Folder 193)
    - (manuscript, pp. 8-15) (Box 3, Folder 194)
  - J. Jeremiah (Jirmejahu)
    - (manuscript, pp. 1-3) (Box 3, Folder 195)
  - K. Psalms (Das Buch der Preisungen)
    - (manuscript and typescript, pp. 1-22) and 1 note (manuscript, p. 1) (Box 3, Folder 196)
- IV. Miscellaneous
  - A. Nahum N. Glatzer's dissertation “Untersuchungen zur Geschichtslehre der Tannaiten”(typescript, handwritten corrections by Martin Buber) (200 pp.) (Box 3, Folder 197)
  - B. Items
    - (manuscript, typescript, telegram and book announcements) (Box 3, Folder 198)
    - (manuscript, typescript and off-prints) (Box 3, Folder 199)
  - C. Envelopes
    - MB to NNG (manuscript and typescript) (20) (Box 3, Folder 200)
    - 1 envelope addressed to Dr. Edward Strauss (manuscript) (Box 3, Folder 201)
    - Leo Baeck to NNG (manuscript)(6 envelopes) (Box 3, Folder 202)
  - D. Notes
    - Lehrhaus or youth center (manuscript, pp. 8) (Box 3, Folder 203)
    - Summary of youth center discussion (typescript, pp. 3) (Box 3, Folder 204)
    - Summary of Martin Goldner lecture (Oct. 23, 1924) (manuscript, pp. 3) (Box 3, Folder 205)
    - Report on Goldner lecture at the Lehrhaus (manuscript, pp. 4) (Box 3, Folder 206)
    - Notes on Bible translation of Romanus Teller (1703-1750) (manuscript, pp. 3) (Box 3, Folder 207)
    - Notes re. FR (manuscript, pp. 4) (Box 3, Folder 208)
    - Notes re. FR’s rabbinical title? (manuscript, pp. 4) (Box 3, Folder 209)
    - Notes re. FR (manuscript, pp. 7) (Box 3, Folder 210)
    - Notes re. FR (Lehrhaus?) (manuscript, pp. 9) (Box 3, Folder 211)
    - MB (manuscript) (Box 3, Folder 212)
    - NNG (Table of Contents?) (typescript, p. 1) (Box 3, Folder 213)
    - Notes for the translation of FR’s Introduction in H. Cohen’s Einleitung in die Jüdische Schriften into Hebrew (manuscript, pp. 28) (Box 3, Folder 214)
    - Notes on FR’s essay, Der Ewige (manuscript, pp. 28) (Box 3, Folder 215)
    - Biblical Essays (NNG outlines and 1 note) (manuscript, pp. 10) (Box 3, Folder 216)
    - Small notes/memos (manuscript) (Box 3, Folder 217)
  - E. Articles
    - Financial records (manuscript) (Box 3, Folder 218)
    - Gift certificates from Schocken Books to MB (Box 3, Folder 219)
    - Editor's postscript to On Judaism NNG (typescript, pp. 8) (Box 3, Folder 220)
    - Newspaper clippings: Book announcement and Recognition of MB as honorary professor at the University of Frankfurt (Box 3, Folder 221)
    - Correspondence and/or study notes (?) (MB and NNG) (manuscript) (Box 3, Folder 222)
    - MB: Signed offprints (3 sheets, 1 envelope) (Box 3, Folder 223)
    - Proofsheet --- “Pharisäertum” in Der Jude (pp. 5) (Box 3, Folder 224)
    - Proofsheet --- “Lebensfrömmigkeit” in Der Jude (pp. 2) (Box 3, Folder 225)
    - Corrections “On Judaism” (NNG) (manuscript, pp. 3) (Box 3, Folder 226)
    - Recept for deposit at local bank (Box 3, Folder 227)
    - Offprint material re. Bible translation (includes duplicates) (Box 3, Folder 228)
    - Offprint material re. Martin Buber (includes duplicates) (Box 3, Folder 229)
    - Material re. Martin Buber (manuscript, copies) (Box 3, Folder 230)